software engineering radio episode 97
interview with Andrew Salzburg this is
software engineering radio the podcast
for professional developers on the web
at s e - radio dotnet se radio prints
irrelevant and detailed discussions and
interviews on soft engineering topics
every 10 days thanks to our audience and
the partners listed on our website for
supporting the program
[Music]
okay welcome listeners to another
episode of software engineering radio
this is another one recall it at
Microsoft in Redmond this time we're
talking to Andres Hattiesburg welcome
Andres thank you and we're going to
start with some historic stuff Andres
has been involved with Pascal while ago
so how did you get into Pascal back then
it was actually sort of in high school I
back in the sort of late later 70's or
mid mid late 70s our high school had
what was then called a mini computer and
on that mini computer we could program
in alcohol and so I was sort of that was
the first programming language I was
taught was alcohol and then when I got
out of high school and into the
Technical University I met up with some
some some buddies there and we started a
company a small you know company to sell
kid computers and makes offer for kid
computers and and I wrote assemblers and
disassemblers and all this kind of stuff
that you you would write for those and
then wanted to write a more of a full
language compiler and I wanted to write
an algorithm piler
because that was what I knew and uh but
then my friend was going you know
there's this new thing called Pascal you
know you should take a look at it you
know and so I did and then it was
actually simpler to implement that I'll
go oh so that's the way it went you know
yeah and and and of course that that was
actually the first Pascal compiler I
wrote was a little the early early
precursor of turbo Pascal and it was all
written in z80
assembler and it was 12 K including the
compiler runtime and an on-screen editor
for this computer called NASSCOM which
was a British kid computer and you could
yank out the Microsoft ROM basic and
then stick in our little pascal compiler
when you turn the power on you were
sitting in an editor you could type code
you know so mm-hmm yeah pascal was
actually the first language that i well
i started with
basic on the Amstrad CPC and then at
school we had Pascal I think it was
turbo has got three things yeah on
seemeth computers and I remember the
time when when I couldn't imagine how
you could program without line numbers I
I was really I don't know how that would
work what are you going to go to anyway
so what's the state of Pascal today is
it is it still used somewhere or is it
it's still you know turbo Pascal is
still or or its predecessor Delphi or
sorry Delphi is I think still used in
education in I forget where but I saw
write-up of it a couple of years ago and
certainly then it still was although I
would say it's it's on the decline for
sure yeah um but but you know I mean
Pascal evolved over many years and you
know sort of sprouted object-orientation
and then sort of become a a fairly
full-fledged language it never really
made the jump into the sort of VM world
and and and byte codes well well that's
actually not entirely true because UCSD
Pascal was really in in a sense the
grandfather of all the byte code systems
because it had P code and R and P code
so if you had like I mean the Apple 2
had a great implementation of UCSD
Pascal and a P code system yeah it's
also not typically cited as you know one
of those precursors to the java vm
people typically talk about probably
goes back too far yeah but it was it was
certainly for me right in inspiration in
in in turbo pascal yeah so you already
mentioned Delphi I used it quite a bit
wrote a couple of hospital data
management system with he felt Delphi 3
or something so why do you think Delphi
was so successful back then I mean it's
obvious competitor was Visual Basic well
I mean I think first lots of credit goes
to visual basic for sorta inventing the
GUI rad tool you know and I I think
that was fantastic but Visual Basic had
all sorts of issues you know I would say
it was in many ways popular in spite of
the fact that it was basic right I mean
they they did so so I there was a market
there for more you know I'd say
industrial-strength language with a real
compiler and native code and you know
real modular compilation and blah blah
blah and so we sort of we sort of
married if you will the radness of that
with a real compiler and then a great
extensibility model that allowed people
to build new components very easily I
mean if you remember Visual Basic for
example did not support inheritance and
you could not create new components by
inheriting from other pros in fact you
couldn't really create new components in
Visual Basic to begin with you write
them in in C using a very complicated
SDK where Delphi was written in itself
and and you know that was actually there
it was a great dog fooding experience
yeah that's always useful so what were
some of the language features off of any
it was called object pascal at that time
mm-hm
it was obviously object oriented but
there was also this component property
event kind of thing can you elaborate on
that a little bit sure well so object
pascal sort of introduced the three
cornerstones of object during program
you know encapsulation inheritance
polymorphism right but it did not really
have a system for writing components and
components is one of those words that
can mean anything but but but you know
it did not have a great model for for
creating sort of visual components that
sit on a tool palette that you can drag
on to a form and then manipulate
properties in a property inspector and
write code behind events and that was in
a sense Delphis contribution to to to
object pascal the fact that we that we
gave first-class treatment to properties
and events in the language and that made
it a lot easier to create these software
components that pretty much every visual
development tool has today it's
all the same paradigm you know we'll
talk about that later in the comes a
sharp but to wrap this Pascale Delfy
thing up what's the state of Delphi
today is it still in production is still
used it's still there it's still used I
mean you know tracker show it but but it
certainly looks to be on the on the
decline
Borland still sells well it's now code
gear but but yeah
but you know I I have to say that Delphi
user community it's an amazingly strong
user community and I would still like
you know there are it's still a great
Windows client - it really is I mean
it's it's something that now I guess
they have a dotnet version although I do
think that most customers probably still
just write native Windows apps whether
or maintain existing native Windows apps
yeah I've heard a rumor that the Condor
soaring simulator is actually written in
Delphi but I have to follow this up I
don't know I wouldn't know yeah it would
be a strange use because it's not at all
forms Windows GUI and there are a lot of
vertical vertical segment windows client
apps written in Delphi mm-hmm more often
than not you run across them in like
like yeah like you said Medical Systems
is what would you say I mean that's like
like I've seen many of them yeah yeah
okay so let's transition a little bit to
the let's say more contemporary at least
you're more contemporary stuff actually
in the beginning of the new year I
completely forgot to ask you to
introduce yourself oh so why don't you
why don't we combine that so you
introduce yourself and tell people what
you're doing today and insurance you
know so my name is Andrew Ellsberg and I
am a technical fellow at Microsoft I
work in the server and tools business
unit or more specifically in the
developer division where I am the chief
architect of the c-sharp programming
language and also sort of the chief
languages strategist if you will further
for for Visual Studio languages c-sharp
many people said or say it's basically a
cross between C C++ kind of things and
the Pascal Delphi world so can you
explain a little bit which of the or
how Delphi influenced or influences
c-sharp mm-hmm well I mean there are you
know you learn from your mistakes and
your successes right and if something
works you keep it and if it doesn't you
get rid of it then so in some ways you
know c-sharp was the language I worked
on after Delphi and I had a different
company at Microsoft instead of it that
Borland yeah and certainly something
that had worked very well for for for
Delphi was this this formalized notion
of properties and events and I felt
strongly that that paradigm our
programming with properties and methods
and events you know had become common
enough that it ought to have first-class
treatment in the language and so that
was one of the sort of core design
tenants of of c-sharp was having
properties and having events as
first-class notions as opposed to Java
say where you have a pattern based
approach and you sort of have to squint
to see the properties you know and
ignore the get and set and the parens
and the methods and so forth yeah and
you don't have events and at all I mean
right you have you have listener
interfaces and whatever and then all
sorts of plumbing in instead yeah yeah
you probably know the Java posse podcast
maybe maybe not oh well you probably
thought yeah no I've heard I've listened
to a few of them yeah that they they
have this guy Joe Nuxhall from from
Apple and he he is this great you know
properties slash event guy and he wants
to put that into Java by all means right
right right
well I mean and there's the whole debate
now in the Java community about closures
which really is sort of like the
underpinning of events if you will its
function pointers or method pointers if
you will and which which c-sharp has had
from day one yeah yeah the syntax has
been getting nicer over the versions
right it will delegate blah blah blah
now you can have real more or less
lambda expressions the syntax for
writing them but the underlying concept
of a method pointer or a delegate is a
method reference this is this has been
the same route yes although generics
makes it a little simpler to declare
them because you can sort of declare one
that's genericized and then write that
use that absolute yeah yeah
so c-sharp
today
we had a discussion with Eric Meyer on
link I think that's probably one of the
most known current new features of
c-sharp and stuff that's kind of hyped
right is there other stuff I mean in the
sense that's a lot talked about a lot
sure yes
so as there are other stuff in in
current c-sharp versions that you think
is innovative compared to let's say
traditional languages or you know what
was interesting for people to know yeah
I you know I feel pretty good about C
sharps evolution I think it's been it's
been very innovative in its in its
various releases you know I mean one
over sort of the the baseline released
that but but nonetheless that that
solidified things like like properties
and events as first-class treatment you
know the unified type system where in
c-sharp everything is an object you know
I mean and then you know later you can
start sort of taking apart the
particulars of value types versus
reference type but there's sort of this
great unifying concept that anything is
an object and then in c-sharp - oh we
added generics and these are reified
generics as opposed to javis erase
generics which which I think history
clearly has proven once what's the right
approach and and I'm very happy with
that work and that was great work done
by Don Simon Andrew Kennedy from
Microsoft Research and now in three oh
we talked about link and because that's
sort of the headliner but the
interesting thing about link is that
first of all it is built on top of
generics and and generics is too deep in
a pleureur for link now is that I don't
see the connection um let me let me let
me let me talk about yours and then
welcome back to why why this but link is
actually an amalgam of language features
about six or seven language features
that come together to form this higher
unity you know so there are things in
there like lambda expressions like
anonymous
types local variable type inference
extension methods object and collection
initializers and so forth and then query
expression or comprehension to that we
sometimes call them and all of those
come together to form this concept of
language integrated query but but the
thing that's interesting is that each of
those features in and of themselves are
quite innovative and quite useful right
I knew of some of them but I didn't put
them onto the link mana yeah yeah no
that is in a sense what link is linked
is built out of those and and and really
the way link came about it's it's an
interesting story because I've always
been fascinated with the impedance
mismatch if you will between general
purpose programming languages and
databases and the fact that here are
these two each and in in and of
themselves incredibly powerful worlds
that are so different and the way they
marry is is is so horrible right I mean
you did it's like there's all this
beauty and general purpose programming
and all this beauty and the relational
algebra on databases and then the way
you put them together is with these
horrible API is right there are queries
and strings and and and so I always felt
like there's got to be a better way and
and of course one of the key key
enablers there is this notion of query
and I always felt that it was bizarre
that you had this incredibly powerful
query engine that only could be used on
data stored in the database right but we
have lots of data and in memory arrays
and expense and and then so but the way
link sorta originally then got
introduced in a language in our
prototypes was just by heart coding
syntax like where and select an order by
like new keywords and and and you know
that compiles into a certain library
function and whatever but but then we
sort of gradually discovered that that
we could generalize this down to just
discreet language features out of which
you get the bigger hole but then you
know it's often this way when when
you're doing new stuff in a language or
any innovative feel for that for that
matter you you sort of plow forward with
a prototype and then you discover that
the prototype is actually just sort of
an instance of a class of solutions and
then if you have the courage you back
up and you put in place the class
instead we did actually do that at one
point in the project we literally
stopped we took all of that stuff out
and then we put in more general concepts
like lambda expressions and extension
methods and so forth and then we built
it all out of that instead and that was
well worth while I think yeah now you
asked why why why generic yes well so
generics make the type system much much
richer and it allows us to flow type
information through complicated
expressions okay so in in link when you
write expression or when you write
queries you're really just sort of like
in a fluent fashion dotting together all
raters should aware select what about
blah blah blah blah blah
these are all generic methods that take
type parameters and then the interplay
between the arguments and the way the
types flow from the arguments into the
results and then become the input to the
next operator
that's all powered by generics if there
were no generics there it's like you
know in order to write a generalized
where operator well it would take you
know I don't know a function that takes
an object and returns an object and - -
you'd cast cast and you would have to
cast everywhere yeah yeah yeah and then
very soon it would no longer look like a
clear language so the other thing is
probably a type inference that if you're
a well - oh yes yes so you've got a
couple at all but oh yes you don't wanna
you don't want to manually have to save
the types and and of course this is why
also in in functional programming
languages that there's so much type
inference because otherwise at all you
know yeah that was one of the the early
early examples installing that you did a
query and then there was the result
which was basically aesthetically type
inferred compiled anonymous type yes
which you could access with the dot
operator you had code completion
everything but you never ever said what
type it was cause it was an animal yes
basically a you know assembled round the
field to select right right yeah so the
type flows out of the query and into
that for each that comes the type down
below yeah very nice the other thing
that I think is fascinating about
linguist it's it's basically it's built
in meta programming facility that you
can get the ast and that's something
it's not very well known but that's
let's say there's not on the forefront
of what people talk about
right it is again one of these enablers
you know when you think about like like
if you really want query to be a
unifying concept where you have you
write your queries in one way arm and
then the execution infrastructure
decides how to how to execute well
sometimes execution isn't even gonna
occur on this machine here like in the
case of a know are map or you want to
take the query turn it into sequel and
put it put in a database or turn it into
I don't know some web-based query
language and send it to Flickr or Amazon
or or or whatever you're writing a link
interface to and in order to do that you
could argue that well maybe we should
like Reverse compiled the il you know
for the for the predicate expressions
and whatever that the user wrote but
that would be horribly complicated it is
not a very IL is not a very
user-friendly format to to grok
expressions in and so that's so hence
there was a need for sort of a
formalization of expression trees yeah
that's really yeah since you mentioned
before that you're the chief language
guy we have to talk a little bit about
language design issues one thing we
already talked about was this notion of
components I don't think we have to
revisit that another thing where I know
that you have a very dedicated opinion
about is exceptions checked exceptions
right so are they good or are they bad
let me answer in two ways I I completely
sympathize with the intent and the
desire to have stronger type-checking I
mean in general type checking or
stronger compile time checking is a good
thing as long as there's another
question related as long as it doesn't
get in your way and that is part two of
the answer is that I think you know when
you weigh the pros and cons it's not
clear to me that you made it better in
the aggregate because checked exceptions
has all have have all sorts of problems
you know with with you know this notion
that you must either handle or yourself
and your method declare that you Reeth
row all of these or or you know push
further push on these exceptions
and of course if you look again if you
look at the job our closures proposal
for example it's yet another example of
how how checked exceptions just really
make your make make your world painful
and and so maybe the dial was dialed up
to higher and so we we certainly felt
that the solutions we knew offered that
we could put in place in c-sharp did not
in the aggregate make make it a better
place to to program and so so we remain
neutral on that we do not have checked
exceptions that's not to say that that
we don't look at having tools like FX
cop and whatever that could do some
analysis on your code and and and and
figure out whether you're handing all
the exceptions and so forth and that's
something we continue to look into
that's a good point that's more but more
like the middle ground right you might
have a system that allows you to trace
what's going on with a tool but you
don't require yeah right right place
also into this general trend of having
more and more powerful studying analysis
tools yes what's your line yes yes yes
another thing that I that I wrote down
is that I think if I look at C sharp and
also at Delphi then you're a big friend
of making your intentions clear by
specifying things like virtual override
yes so that you can cross-check whether
you know things fit together right yeah
this this was um again actually I think
that at this time we got right in Delphi
and that that that was carried forward
into c-sharp is this notion that you
[Music]
must specifically say that you are
overriding a virtual method like like if
you contrast it with C++ or or or Java
or at least in Java you override a
virtual method just by saying the
virtual vault you don't first of all you
never say virtual everything's virtual
by default which which I also don't
agree with but but but but you override
the method simply by by restating and
it's and it's just the coincidence that
you used to say name means and signature
means that it's an override and that is
effectively a sort of a versioning
timebomb you know because as a base
class evolves it is likely at some point
to introduce
a method with the same name and
signature as a method that exists in a
user derived class that was written
before and now all of a sudden that
becomes an override but there's no
guarantee that the semantics intent was
the same here and so now all of a sudden
you're gonna get calls to this method
that you never expected to get or you're
gonna get or worse you're gonna get
compile time errors because the
signature matches but the return type
doesn't and so and this has indeed
happened as the Java libraries have
evolved you know this versioning bomb
has gone off from and how does the
override mode and what if I prevent that
I mean because if you if you just write
override oh well okay I see of course
you cannot write override when at the
time you write you say right there must
be something to override or else you get
a compile time here huh right and if you
don't say override then you introduce a
new method here and this method may have
the same name and signatures will never
be but then you're just hiding that one
view you're shadowing it yeah so yeah
there are other examples in languages of
this kind of thing where you where you
specify you know with certain keywords
or modifiers was actually going on so
that these kinds of things cannot happen
um well for example the way we treat
interfaces and interface implementations
in in c-sharp also makes you be a little
more specific about how you implement
and for example we support private
interface implementations where you can
specifically implement this method of
this interface you know by saying
interface name dot method if you haven't
many interfaces in a class right right
and they show happen to ya they so
happen to have a method with the same
name and signature and in Java there's
no way to have these two implementations
and that also does happen and it's also
an example of sort of a versioning
problem so we we try to in the design of
c-sharp think a lot about making it
versioning resilient because it's one of
those things that that sort of makes the
language live longer it's it's the kind
of thing that doesn't matter at all in
v1 and then as you come down like ten
years later it matters a whole bunch
because there are big code bases and you
have not painted yourself into a corner
with respect to introducing new features
I think a good example of seeing some of
the consequences of that is the Eclipse
platform it's written in Java
and they have all kinds of evolution
nightmares you know blah blah blah in
there is such-and-such
two three four right right I'm obviously
not everything is a consequence of those
missing yeah I mean interfaces in
general you cannot introduce new methods
you know because you're bad cells other
stuff it's also implementation yes it's
just it shows this is a platform that is
very long-lived and they they really
have a challenge of handling the
evolution of the things without breaking
old stuff right so let's let let's look
a little bit at languages of the future
since your strategist you have to know
what they are so one provocative
statement I've I've read several times
and you know as as long as it looks like
see so you can invent any language you
want you can invent any language feature
you want you have to use curly braces of
course that's a little bit cynical but
but where do you think the the the
likely made this statement I don't know
it might have been Steve Agee in wises
I'm not sure okay so what do you think
are important concepts in upcoming
languages well I don't think the curly
brace it nests of a languages is is
gonna and certainly you look at that
languages like Python and and say F
sharp and whatever I there's they're
precious few curly braces and I do think
that if you look at what is the
underlying trend of programming language
if go back like like all these what 4050
years that we've had them now and it's
it's really the one thing that that
continues to happen is that we increase
the level of abstraction right of our of
our programming languages right we
started with plug boards and then you
know machine code and assembler and then
C and n C++ and now we're now we're sort
of in managed languages like like Java
and c-sharp and dynamic languages are
seeing a resurgence and and whatever and
and so really I see no I see no
indication that that that is changing
mm-hm
meaning that really the next thing is
going to be some some upping up the
abstraction level again and that that
the challenge is identifying what
what that new abstraction is gonna be
and that sort of largely influenced by
by what's happening in in in the
industry today which which is that you
know Moore's law has not stopped working
but it's changed in nature in that it's
not gonna give us higher clock speeds
anymore right it will still continue and
and everybody thinks for at least in a
10 10 20 years to to increase density
and and and capacity they already better
yet the over but but but it comes now in
the form of more CPUs instead of faster
C values it's really sort of like the
the bottom line right and that means all
of a sudden concurrency is so much more
important than it used to be now
currencies always been important in
certain domains like high performance
computing and then and whatever and and
and and graphics processing and and but
but now it's starting to actually become
important to mainstream computing
because it is the only way that we're
gonna harness the power so to speak and
and and of course as a programming
language designer that means that we
need to think deeply about how we can do
better models for concurrency because I
firmly believe that the models we have
today do not scale to general masses of
application programmers is one reason
why I agree and I think everybody agrees
is more or less exempt for the Olin guys
who obviously know so it's one reason
why concurrency is so complicated today
that it's not part of the language but
rather part of libraries so it's hard to
check how to and the compiler can give
you a very limited support you have a
lot of protocols you agreed to as
opposed to having formal specification
yeah I think you know I think the big
killer is state or rather mutable state
you know and we have effectively taught
programmers like generations of
programmers that hey state is wonderful
and you're free to mutate it whenever
you feel like it you know like hey
declare self an array and then just
start poking elements in there and empty
in for loops and what
you and and that's fine as long as
everything executed serially there's no
problem and then along comes concurrency
and parallelism and all of a sudden you
have multiple units of work mutating the
same state and you can't even begin to
reason about it and and there's very
little in our languages that provide the
necessary framework for reasoning about
it so in a sense you could say yeah it's
because it's API although you know I
mean we do have we do have locks or
synchronization sort of as language
features but they're very low-level
features yes we try not have
higher-level concepts like this thing is
guaranteed to be isolated or this thing
is concurrency safe whatever or this
thing this function is pure or this dude
you know this this object is immutable a
lot of these things are not language
concept right and and ideally they
should be but we don't necessarily know
how to make them I mean you could argue
some of them we've we know what a
solution might look like there are pure
functional programming languages and and
you know and they are indeed wonderful
for concurrency they're just not so
wonderful for writing real application
so that isn't you know that isn't the
answer either right but but we can
borrow some from there and there are
certainly parts of applications that
don't need to be as mutable in their
state management as they are today yeah
at Q come two weeks ago I saw Ted nerds
talk on f-sharp and then Simon paid and
Jones talked about Haskell mm-hm
so and they both of course are
functional and ideally more or less pure
functional and they of course also
talked about the fact that this is
really great for concurrency mm-hm and
I've heard many other talks that
basically had the same message but what
I haven't heard yet is a talk that tells
me okay
here is functional stuff and then there
is the other stuff that has side effects
because at some point you have to have
side effects so what do you implement
with which of those how do you
distinguish them what how much
concurrency do you put in infrastructure
/ architecture you know application
servers and stuff how much is necessary
in the language level like if you look
at Erlang for example the fact that it's
functional is not not really important
the fact that the reason why it is so
good for concurrency is because it has
this active
yeah and yeah it wouldn't no be would be
no problem if you had imperative and
chaired stayed within an actor well as
long as it's isolated right but but
right right exactly so but so Erlang
formalizes the notion of isolation or
goes further in formalizing the notion
of isolation why don't you have an
isolated domain then sure you can have
you can have mutation in there to your
heart's content because you're
guaranteed that there's only one threat
of execution at a time and it's it's
stuff like that where we have to but but
but this but then this doesn't really
work this doesn't help you one damn with
if you're writing you know a data
parallel application that's going to do
matrix multiplication or or or or
whatever right so so there are many
different forms of concurrency if you
will and we need to sort of push the
state of the art therein in coming up
with programming models that are more
suitable than what we have today and
then and then you know after that comes
then formalization in the language of
those programming models in a sense I
one thing that gives me hope is that
that with all of the stuff that we've
done and in insane in my domain and in
c-sharp
um the language actually has become
incredibly rich and you can start you
can start experimenting with concurrent
programming models simply by writing
api's and api's have become rich enough
now that you can almost create little
domain-specific languages just as AP is
now a link is an example of that right
we have another example in the the
threat parallel library or TPL that our
concurrency group is building they're
actually building two technologies
together TP l and p link which is a
parallel implementation of linq and
they're just api's but they're very rich
api's that take advantage of generics
and type inference and so forth and and
through those it's almost like you can
introduce new statements you know like
parallel dot for you know it's really a
function but you pass to it the body of
code you want to execute so in a sense
it's like a method right are like a like
like a statement so what i understand
from that is that in addition to solving
the concurrency challenge in future
languages i think having them more
expressive may be through means of
concepts borrowed from functional
programming yes and you know first-class
functions yes probably another important
well it's important because it allows if
you if you if you try to build you know
a new programming model for concurrency
bike by noodling with the keywords in
the language or and then you try to do
all the language work upfront well you
have a couple of problems one is you
might get it wrong and now you put some
stuff into the language that you can
never get rid of again and now you've
aged the language and the language will
therefore become irrelevant sooner and
that's a problem right problem number
two is that there's only you thinking
about the problem not your entire user
community the other way around
instead of adding the instance to the
language you add the class that allows
the users to create the instances so to
speak then you get a much broader user
community experimenting in the field and
you can then in a sense as a language
designer cherry-pick and go wow this
thing is becoming very popular maybe we
should think about having formalized you
know like comprehensions or or
statements that that are just a pattern
over that API right like for each's for
example in c-sharp right it's just a
pattern or using enumerators and link
expressions are just a pattern over the
link api pattern so that's sort of what
i think is the better way forward if you
will so that also hints in the direction
of meta programming slash
domain-specific languages sure before
you said that you are a big fan of
static typing you didn't say it
explicitly but it became quite obvious
so how do you think meta programming
dsls goes together with static typing I
mean most of the internal layers else
can be seen in dynamic like which is
like right right right well it's
interesting because yeah people just I
like to like like a little tangent there
you know I I think one of the reasons
that languages like like Ruby for
example or Python or B are becoming
popular is is really in many ways in
spite of the fact that that they are not
typed but spot because of the fact that
they do very good
metaprogramming support static typing is
is I you know I don't see a lot of
downside to static typing other than the
fact that it may not be practical to put
in place and it is harder to put in
place yes ah you know and therefore it
takes longer for us to get there with
static typing but once you do have
static typing I mean gosh you know like
hey the compilers gonna report the
errors before the space shuttle flies
instead of whilst it's flying right
that's a good thing
you get productivity tools like
statement completion which like if I
were to take that away from programmers
the way there would be there I mean I
would be dethroned immediately and and
someone else will be put in place and
they'd have to reinstate it right
because it is such a productivity tool
and better of refactorings you know
require has better knowledge of types
you know so and and and static program
analysis and whatever like performance
optimizations blah blah blah I mean
there's a long laundry list of things
that static typing is the enabler of so
so I continue to think it's important
now with respect to to dsls I don't know
if you know we think a lot about dsls
and and I think there are a bunch of
things we've already done in c-sharp 300
that make it a better place for creating
dsls you know like expression trees is
is is definitely an enabler there and we
will look at growing expression trees
into becoming statement trees where you
can express full method bodies if you
will as as trees and pass them around as
arguments and manipulate them and so
forth and in many ways I you know I
think it's important for us to to work
on creating a better ecosystem better
API is better infrastructure for dynamic
program construction if you look at
people tend to think that all word
there's all this resurgence of dynamic
languages and you know we're becoming
more and more dynamic you know well but
we're actually doing very dynamic things
with static languages look at look at
something like asp.net for example which
is huge dynamic programming system you
drop in aspx page into into a directory
and poof you know oh someone notices
that it's newer and gostrey compiles it
turns it into into
into native code that it then runs but
it's totally dynamic right but the way
we get there sometimes through code
generators and whatever is somewhat
complicated and we could have we could
have api's that allows you to
dynamically generate statically type
programs there's another interesting
thing there which is this notion that we
are all sort of wired in our heads to
associate dynamic programming with lack
of typing and Static programming with
strong type right and that doesn't have
to be that way and I in I actually think
that the ideal place to be is static
programming but but dynamically
generated if you follow I think I mean
there's no reason why we should not do
better type checking in a dynamic
scenario as well
mm-hmm so of course I mean if you have
this typical Ruby case where you call a
method that doesn't exist and you have
method missing invoked or whatever it's
called in Ruby right you know I don't
know how to handle this what should I do
right you can't do this in a statically
typed language because the compiler
wouldn't let you call this method
because it's not there right so right
you have to introduce some let's say
type system holes like dot dot meaning
instead of thought that you could do it
through dot I mean so so yeah you're
sort of pointing out that that that I
mean but but I will first say that you
know the fact that you sometimes want to
do something dynamic doesn't mean that
it should always agree on emphasis oh so
you could certainly speculate about
formalizing the notion of dynamic
dispatch in a statically typed language
and that's something that I find to be
very interesting and something that we
might do in in a future C sharp now we
could do it through a special dot
operator or we could do it through
static typing we could say if the thing
your dotting on is of a type that says I
am dynamic am ending the I dynamic is or
whatever is yeah yeah and the dispatch
is dynamic right so again static typing
actually allows you to to do different
things for dynamic dispatch right yeah
yeah that's really interesting that
you're thinking about this stuff because
that's stuff that I'm so I'm really
interested in Scala if not it feels
almost like a functional sorry a dynamic
language for a brief time and stuff yes
but it doesn't it is not dynamic right
cuz I'm not a fan of dynamic branches
for so they're interesting discussion
right yeah no this is
I mean I think one of the people wanted
one of the one of the examples that
people cite in in in c-sharp
3 is local variable type inference and
the fact you just say var Rx equals
something and it looks just like
JavaScript you know what it is actually
strongly typed yeah so um to to come
towards the end slowly but certainly you
said before that if if somebody takes
away the statement completion feature
then I'm basically screwed so I think
one really important cornerstone in
future language development is that
there is no point in developing a
language without thinking about the tool
that you use right to work with the
language right so can you talk a little
bit about accept well in addition to is
they've been completing refactoring
which is kind of obvious how language
design might change in the future when
we take into account the tooling aspect
as a first-class ingredient to language
design um that's that's actually a very
fascinating area and I've always been a
strong believer in symbiosis between
tool and language and framework that's
the third ingredient that's that sort of
that yeah and I mean in a sense if you
look at like turbo Pascal I mean it was
it was about more tightly marrying those
right and that was that was really what
what fueled its success and that's how
all modern IDs look look today and it's
it I think it's foolish to think about
one to the exclusion of the other
because in our day to day lives you know
I mean as programmers we don't really
sit there and make a distinction between
whether this is a keyword or an API or
whether you know I mean it's it's just
you know it's important for for this to
be deeply deeply integrated now what
were you you were asking about
oh yeah how does it affect how does it
affect language design or does it or
does it well it absolutely does um
here's a good example like like with
link and this is very very relevant
really um if you if you program with
link you will have noticed that the
select clause in a query comes at the
end of of the query you say from blah
blah blah where or if I group by blah
blah blah and then finally in
select now there are certain API reasons
why that makes sense because you know
the select is the last thing you do you
know - - but but but we could have
certainly in our query comprehensions
put the Select clause first like sequel
does select field one for select blah
blah blah from blah blah blah where blah
blah blah but think about what the
statement completion experience for that
would be now Here I am typing query
equals select space what I sure you
don't know what are we sure you what
everything that known to mankind or we
have no we have no idea where things are
coming from yet so yeah but if you say
from blah blah blah you know where now
we know what's in scope so we can show
you what what and and so so that was one
you know to us deep motivator actually
for for putting things in in in the
other order if you will be be vb9
in its original prototypes have to
select clause first and they did run
into this statement completion problem
you know and you would have effectively
have to write select and then you'd sort
of have to write from blah blah blah and
then go back to the Select and now you
could get statement provision and it
didn't work so well very nice example
yeah so another thing that I always
think of but I can't really probably
computed in words is that somehow if you
have a static language which supports
meta programming kind of things that the
IDE would have to understand all that
stuff too much deeper extend so that it
could actually understand what you just
met our program yes so they get into a
pond and the compiled on you that I
don't know so I think it makes things
more complicated absolutely it does and
and there is you know I am fascinated by
dsls but there's a part of me that also
worries about dsls because
today we have to deal with one language
not a thousand languages you know like
in in a sense with dsl x' every program
becomes its own language right and and
that that could be dangerous by domain I
mean that's depending on how easy of
course you make it how much you push it
and then and and and whatever hello yeah
there's there so it's it's yeah it's a
tricky issue yeah so so to wrap this
thing up do you want to mention a couple
of interesting upcoming see
top features first published audacity
radio no I mean bet them no no their old
man is there any well I think you know
in in in general I can tell you that
about the big influencers right and
we've already talked to Brian current
she is huge and and we're we're gonna do
something I don't know what the sulk is
but we're definitely thinking about it
domain-specific language is
metaprogramming whatever you've all
you've already seen this take steps
there and it's and it's an important
influencer and dynamic languages are
important and in you know and when I say
dynamic languages I don't just mean you
know like like like Python Ruby and
whatever I mean dynamic styles are
programming right and and that has lots
of impact on c-sharp as well you know so
or will have impact on C sharp as well
but but exactly what the features look
like you know I couldn't tell you guys I
don't know yet yeah okay anything else
you want to leave our listeners with any
pearls of wisdom you know and nothing
comes to mind right now you know but you
know but other than you know as usual we
live in interesting times you know and
and and we definitely you know you would
think by now that that we'd be done but
but challenges just seem to get bigger
all the time yeah that's a good thing
the more we know the bigger of people
well the bigger the challenge people
want us to write yes yes all we can hope
is just that that that that we don't
sort of fall victim to the old adage of
you knew that it couldn't be done and
therefore you never tried right I mean
and they're okay Anders thank you very
very much for interview oh my pleasure
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
SE - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
by on the website or you can advertise
for se radio for example by clicking on
the Digg reddit delicious and slash dog
buttons to contact the team leaves an
email to team and su radio net or if
it's specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can read and react to your
comments this episode of software
engineering radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under Creative
Commons license please see the website
for details thanks to Charlie crowd and
the pot site Music Network for the music
used in this show the song is called
Vegas hard rock shuffle
[Music]